Guide to the James Rowland Angell Personal Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
James Rowland Angell personal papers
1833-1986
1880-1947
MS 2
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
19.75
Correspondence, which makes up the bulk of the papers, together with writings, speeches, reports, printed matter and photographs. The family correspondence contains a long series of letters (1890-1894) from Marion Isabel Watrous before her marriage to Angell in 1894. Prominent among his professional correspondents are Charles Bakewell, John Dewey, William James, A.H. Pierce and George Dudley Seymour. Also included are papers relating to Angell's inauguration as president of Yale University and his term of office. Additional papers include minutes and reports of the Rockefeller Foundation and of the General Education Board (also endowed by Rockefeller funds) on both of which James R. Angell served as member and trustee. The minutes and reports of the General Education Board document its support for various programs to reorganize general education in the United States and to improve education for women, blacks and children. The minutes of the Rockefeller Foundation detail its support for research projects in the natural sciences and the humanities.
Angell, James Rowland, 1869-1949
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. James Rowland Angell, 1967, Katharine B. Woodman, 1983, 1987, and Alfred H. Fuchs, 2005.
Arrangement
Arranged in six series and additions: I. Personal Documents and Papers. II. Correspondence. II. Writings. IV. Printed Materials. V. Newspaper Clippings and Photographs. Oversize.
Separated Materials
Two record albums ("The Last President of NBC — This is your Company" and "A Presidential Proclamation.") concerning Mr. Angell's career with the National Broadcasting Company are located in the Historical Sound Recordings department. Two engravings that belonged to him, The Turner Gallery and Piante di Roma, can be found in the graphic Arts Collection of the library.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence, which makes up the bulk of the papers, together with writings, speeches, reports, printed matter and photographs. The family correspondence contains a long series of letters (1890-1894) from Marion Isabel Watrous before her marriage to Angell in 1894. Prominent among his professional correspondents are Charles Bakewell, John Dewey, William James, A.H. Pierce and George Dudley Seymour. Also included are papers relating to Angell's inauguration as president of Yale University and his term of office. Additional papers include minutes and reports of the Rockefeller Foundation and of the General Education Board (also endowed by Rockefeller funds) on both of which James R. Angell served as member and trustee. The minutes and reports of the General Education Board document its support for various programs to reorganize general education in the United States and to improve education for women, blacks and children. The minutes of the Rockefeller Foundation detail its support for research projects in the natural sciences and the humanities.
Note: The Presidential Papers of J.R. Angell (RU 24) are cataloged separately from his personal papers.
Biographical / Historical
James Rowland Angell was born in Burlington, Vermont, on May 8, 1869. Shortly afterwards his family moved to Ann Arbor, Michigan, where his father, James Burrill Angell, became President of the University of Michigan. As a young boy he accompanied his father on a trip around the world and spent a year and a half in China. James was the youngest of three children; his sister, Lois, was six years his senior and his brother, Alexis, twelve.
After graduating from the Ann Arbor public schools in 1886, he entered the University of Michigan where he received his A.B. degree in 1890. Although during his freshman year he followed the classical course, as an upperclassman he elected work in philosophy and psychology. He continued these studies as a graduate student at the University of Michigan and, under the guidance of John Dewey, received his M.A. degree with philosophy as a major and economics and American history as minors. In 1891 he left Michigan to work under William James at Harvard. He went to Germany the following year where he studied at the universities of Berlin and Halle and completed a Ph.D. thesis in German on Kant. Before receiving his degree, Mr. Angell returned to the United States to assume a teaching position at the University of Minnesota. His teaching career was continued at the University of Chicago where, in 1904, he was promoted to a professorship in experimental psychology. In 1911 he became Dean of the Faculties and, after a brief period in Washington during World War I, became Acting President of the University of Chicago. At the end of the war, he was elected to membership in the National Academy of Sciences and was appointed Chairman of the National Research Council. He was invited to become President of the Carnegie Corporation in 1920. Mr. Angell was also editor of Psychological Monographs from 1912 to 1922.
When the Yale Corporation approached him with the offer of the Yale Presidency in 1921, they broke a two century tradition of selecting only Yale graduates for that office. During the sixteen years of Angell's Presidency, the Yale School of Nursing, the Department of Drama, the Institute of Human Relations, the Yale Observatory at Johannesburg, and many important professorships came into being. Under the direction of his shrewd business judgement, the university endowment funds increased fourfold and building programs affecting Yale's library, gym, art gallery, law school and medical school were undertaken. Angell's years as Yale's President were outstanding for their educational leadership as well as their able administration.
After retiring from Yale in 1937, Mr. Angell became educational consultant for the National Broadcasting Company. In the years which followed he continued his interest in Yale, became a trustee of the American Museum of Natural History and, after 1944, a director of the Hall of Fame.
During his career as educator and psychologist, Mr. Angell was active in numerous organizations, wrote several books and received many awards. His membership in associations included the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, the American Psychological Association, the American Philosophical Society, the National Academy of Science, the English-Speaking Union, Phi Beta Kappa, Delta Kappa Epsilon and Kappa Delta Pi. Psychology, his first book, was followed by Chapters in Modern Psychology in 1911, Introduction to Psychology in 1913 and American Education in 1937. Mr. Angell also wrote many articles in scientific journals. Among the honors he received were the French Legion of Honor and the Grand Officer of the Order of the Crown of Italy.
James Rowland Angell married Marion Isabel Watrous in 1894. Their son, James Waterhouse Angell, is a noted economist, and their daughter, Marion, the former wife of William Rockefeller McAlpin. After Mrs. Angell's death in 1931, Mr. Angell was married to Katherine Cramer Woodman. They resided at 155 Blake Road, Hamden, Connecticut, until Mr. Angell's death in 1949.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
African Americans -- Education; Courtship; Education -- United States; Endowments; Psychology; Women -- Education; Asia; Connecticut; Photographs; Educators; Psychologists; Angell, James Rowland, 1869-1949; Angell, Marion Isabel Watrous; Angell, Sarah S.C.; Bakewell, Charles M. (Charles Montague), 1867-1957; Dewey, John, 1859-1952; Eliot, Charles William, 1834-1926; Gay, Edwin F. (Edwin Francis), 1867-1946; James, William, 1842-1910; Pierce, Arthur Henry, 1867-1914; Seymour, George Dudley, 1859-1945; Council on Foreign Relations; General Education Board (New York, N.Y.); Rockefeller Foundation; Yale University -- Employees; Yale University -- Presidents
- PERSONAL DOCUMENTS AND PAPERS, 1881-1947; Series I; .75 linear feet (2 boxes, 1 folio)
  Scope and Contents
  The series is subdivided into two subseries, personal documents and personal papers.
  Personal Documents consist of documents related to Yale University, documents related to his inauguration as President of Yale University, an oversized blue folder with inaugural greetings from foreign universities arranged alphabetically by name of country and followed by greetings from several universities in the United States and a book from the Secretary's Office at Yale University containing the invitation list to President Angell's inauguration; also, miscellaneous documents concerned with Mr. Angell's personal affairs including a probate court notice, a personal property assessment for Chicago's Hyde Park and a Report to Policyholders from the Equitable Life Assurance Society in 1894; finally, documents officially presented to Mr. Angell as awards or honorary gifts, including his certificates from the French Legion of Honor and the Grand Officer of the Order of the Crown of Italy, as well as correspondence relating to his receiving these awards, and a gold embossed copy of the Lieutenant Governor's Address to the Connecticut State Senate in 1929.
  Personal Papers consist of biographical sketches of James Rowland Angell and James Burrill Angell (correspondence relating to these contained Series II, folders 115 and 186) and a genealogy of the Angell family (correspondence related to this in Series II, folder 157); papers and records pertaining to Mr. Angell's education at Harvard University and membership in the Old Colonial Historical Association and Harvard's Graduate Club; two diaries written by Mr. Angell during the year and a half he spent as a boy in China; invoices, receipts, a savings book and other banking information; invitations to Presidential receptions, Colonial Club gatherings, weddings, church related events and a citizenship rally; itinerary of Mr. Angell as President of Yale University; dinner invitations and menus; and a miscellaneous folder which includes a published reply to Angell's first speech at Yale and a poem in his honor by George Parmly Day.
  - Personal Documents
    - Personal documents related to Yale, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Inaugural greetings, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      General
      See: box 32
    - Invitation list to Angell's inauguration, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous, 1891-1914 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - French Legion of Honor, 1929-1932 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Italian Government: Grand Officer of the Order of the Crown of Italy, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Connecticut's Lieutenant Governor's Address to the State Senate, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Personal Papers
    - Biographical sketch of James Rowland Angell, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 7a)
    - Biographical sketch of James Burrill Angell, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 7b)
    - Genealogy of Angell family, undated (Box 2, Folder 7c)
    - Education, 1892-1895 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Membership in associations, 1895-1921 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Diary from travel in China, 1881 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Financial, 1884-1944 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Invitations and announcements, 1891-1936 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Itinerary of James Rowland Angell as President of Yale University, 1921-1937 (Box 2, Folder 12a)
    - Dinner engagements, 1892-1927 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Miscellaneous, 1894-1947 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- CORRESPONDENCE, (1874), 1880-1947, (1949-1850); Series II; 8.5 linear feet (22 Boxes)
  The correspondence is divided into two subseries: Family Correspondence and General Correspondence.
  Family Correspondence consists of letters to James Rowland Angell from members of his family between 1880 and 1947 and of correspondence of members of James Rowland Angell's family with relatives and personal friends between 1891 and 1910.
  The letters to James Rowland Angell from family members do not include replies from him, except for a letter written to Marion Watrous, his fiancée and subsequent wife, in 1890, a folder of letters he sent to her from chicago in 1909, and a few other letters and telegrams. The letters are arranged by the names of Mr. Angell's correspondents, which are listed in a genealogical sequence according to their relationship to James Rowland Angell. A major portion of the letters are from his father, James B. Angell, written between 1891 and 1910 (19 folders), his mother, Sarah S. C. Angell, between 1890 and 1903 (16 folders), and his wife, Marion Angell, from 1890 to 1921 (29 folders). At the end of the letters for each of these correspondents is a folder containing letters for which no year has been indicated or fragments of letters whose dates are not known. In the correspondence from his mother and wife, letters which exclude the month and/or the day, but not the year in which they were written, are included at the end of the folder for that particular year. Several letters of this type were received from his wife in 1909 and are grouped together in folder 80. A folder of unidentified family letters ranging from 1891 to 1935 is enclosed in folder 92.
  The correspondence of James Rowland Angell's family with relatives and personal friends includes a group of letters addressed to Mrs. Sarah Angell which contains correspondence from her brother, Thomas Thompson Caswell, her sister-in-law, Harriet B. Caswell, and a personal friend, E.A. Shepard. The other group of letters were written to Marion Angell. Most of these were from Sarah and James B. Angell; the remainder were sent by her sister-in-law, Lois Angell McLaughlin, her brother, Phillip Watrous and from three personal friends.
  Letters written by the family of his second wife, Katherine Angell during the late 19th and early 20th centuries were originally included in this series. However, since she did not marry Mr. Angell until 1934 and these letters had no references to him or to his family, the correspondence was returned to Mrs. Katherine Angell in February, 1969.
  General Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by the name of the institution or individual corresponding with James Rowland Angell. This alphabetical sequence also includes letters whose contents deal with some subject, such as the biographical sketch of Mr. Angell, and letters from abroad, listed according to the name of the country from which they were sent. The letters within the folders are organized chronologically with two exceptions: correspondence with foreign countries is arranged under the name of the country in alphabetical order according to the names of individual correspondents, and the individual authors and editors of monographs to be published by the Psychological Review Company are listed alphabetically under "Psychological Monographs" Material other than letters — such as minutes, announcements, reports and programs —are located at the end of the folder or, if numerous, contained in additional folders following the correspondence. Letters whose authors could not be identified are located in folder 306.
  The contents of the letters concern Mr. Angell's personal and professional activities before, during and after his Presidency at Yale. Among the earlier letters are those from prominent colleagues such as Charles Bakewell, John Dewey, Alfred S. Hodden, William James and A. H. Pierce. The correspondence listed under Yale University includes the numerous congratulatory letters he received upon his election in 1921, which are filed according to the date they were written and followed by a folder of Mr. Angell's replies. Although not all of the congratulatory letters were answered, Mr. Angell's secretary indicated in pencil on the original letter the date the response was written. The material concerning his retirement is divided into several topics, such as personal tributes and parties held in honor of Mr. Angell.
  - Family Correspondence
    - Letters to James Rowland Angell from his father, James Burrill Angell, 1891 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Letters to J.R. Angell from J.B. Angell, 1892-1897 (Box 3, Folder 16-21)
    - Letters to J.R. Angell from J.B. Angell, 1898-1910 (Box 4, Folder 22-32)
    - Letters with no year indicated, fragments (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Letters to James Rowland Angell from his mother, Sarah S.C. Angell, 1890-1891 (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - Letters to J.R. Angell from S.S.C. Angell, January-May 1892, July-December 1892, January-December 1893, January-December 1894 (Box 5, Folder 35-40)
    - Letters to J.R. Angell from S.S.C. Angell, 1895-1899 (Box 6, Folder 41-45)
    - Letters to J.R. Angell from S.S.C. Angell, 1900-1903 (Box 7, Folder 46-48)
    - Letters with no year indicated (Box 7, Folder 49)
    - Correspondence of James Rowland Angell with his brother, Alexis Caswell Angell, 1880-1894, 1920-1934 (Box 8, Folder 50)
    - Correspondence of James Rowland Angell with his brother's wife, Fannie C.C. Angell, 1881-1894 (Box 8, Folder 51)
    - Correspondence of James Rowland Angell with his nephew, Frank Angell, 1922-1933 (Box 8, Folder 52)
    - Correspondence of James Rowland Angell with his nephew, James B. Angell, 1934 (Box 8, Folder 53)
    - Correspondence of James Rowland Angell with his sister, Lois Angell McLaughlin, 1891-1935 (Box 8, Folder 54)
    - Letters to James Rowland Angell from his sister's husband, Andrew C. McLaughlin, 1891-1893 (Box 8, Folder 55)
    - Letters to James Rowland Angell from his maternal grandfather, Alexis Caswell, 1874, 1894 (Box 8, Folder 56)
    - Letters to James Rowland Angell from his first wife, Marion Angell, 1890 (Box 9, Folder 57)
    - Letters to J.R. Angell from M. Angell, April-December 1891, January-May 1892, July-December 1892 (Box 9, Folder 58-63)
    - Letters to J.R. Angell from M. Angell, January-December 1893, January-April 1894 (Box 10, Folder 64-67)
    - Letters to J.R. Angell from M. Angell, May-December 1894 (Box 11, Folder 68-69)
    - Letters with no month or day indicated, 1894 (Box 11, Folder 70)
    - Letters to J.R. Angell from M. Angell, 1895-1900 (Box 11, Folder 71-75)
    - Letters to J.R. Angell from M. Angell, 1901, 1903-1906, 1909 (Box 12, Folder 76-78)
    - Letters from James Rowland Angell to Marion Angell, 1909 (Box 12, Folder 79)
    - Letters to J.R. Angell from M. Angell with no month or day indicated, 1909 (Box 12, Folder 80)
    - Letters to J.R. Angell from M. Angell, 1910, 1920-1921 (Box 12, Folder 81-82)
    - Letters to J.R. Angell from M. Angell with no year indicated, undated (Box 12, Folder 83)
    - Fragments of Marion Angell's letters, undated (Box 12, Folder 84)
    - Poem to James Rowland Angell from Marion Angell, undated (Box 12, Folder 85)
    - Letters to James Rowland Angell from his son, James W. Angell, 1909-1910, 1925, 1930-1933 and 1946 (Box 12, Folder 86)
    - Letters to James Rowland Angell from his son's wife, Jane W. Angell with no year indicated, undated (Box 12, Folder 87)
    - Letters to James Rowland Angell from his daughter, Marion (Molly) Angell, 1909-1946 (Box 12, Folder 88)
    - Letters to James Rowland Angell from his father-in-law, Mr. C.L. Watrous, 1891 (Box 12, Folder 89)
    - Letters to James Rowland Angell from his mother-in-law, Mrs. Sophia Watrous, 1891-1893 (Box 12, Folder 90)
    - Letters to James Rowland Angell from his brother-in-law, Mr. Phillip Watrous, 1894 (Box 12, Folder 91)
    - Unidentified family letters, 1891-1935 (Box 12, Folder 92)
    - Letters to Sarah Angell from her (Box 13, Folder 93)
      - brother, Thomas Thompson Caswell, 1891 (Box 13, Folder 93)
      - sister-in-law, Harriet B. Caswell, 1891 (Box 13, Folder 93)
      - personal friend, E.A. Shepard, undated (Box 13, Folder 93)
      - unidentified letter to Sarah Angell, undated (Box 13, Folder 93)
    - Letter from Alexis Caswell to Samuel M. Castle, 1875 (Box 13, Folder 93a)
    - Letters to Marion Angell from her father-in-law, James B. Angell, 1908-1910 (Box 13, Folder 94)
    - Letters to Marion Angell from her mother-in-law, Sarah Angell, 1890-1909 (Box 13, Folder 95)
    - Letter to Marion Angell from her sister-in-law, Lois Angell McLaughlin, 1893 (Box 13, Folder 96)
    - Letter to Marion Angell from her brother, Phillip Watrous, 1909 (Box 13, Folder 97)
    - Letters to Marion Angell from personal friends, 1909 (Box 13, Folder 98)
  - General Correspondence
    - Addresses, correspondence regarding, 1921 (Box 14, Folder 99)
    - American Museum of Natural History, 1937 (Box 14, Folder 100)
    - American Philosophical Association, 1931-1932 (Box 14, Folder 101)
    - American Philosophical Society
      - Correspondence, 1924-1936 (Box 14, Folder 102)
      - Laws and rules, list of members and nominees for membership, reports, progress bulletins, 1921-1937 (Box 14, Folder 103)
      - General and business meetings, announcements and, invitations, 1924-1937 (Box 14, Folder 104)
    - American Psychological Association
      - Correspondence, 1922-1937 (Box 14, Folder 105)
      - Yearbook, minutes, report, elections, requests for papers, announcements and programs of meetings, 1921-1937 (Box 14, Folder 106)
    - Arnold, Arnold: dog bite episode, 1934 (Box 14, Folder 107)
    - Ashley, M.L., 1898 (Box 15, Folder 108)
    - Bacon, Seldon, 1894 (Box 15, Folder 109)
    - Bakewell, Charles M., 1893-1899 (Box 15, Folder 110)
    - Ball, William Dearborn, 1892-1894 (Box 15, Folder 111)
    - Bannon, Arthur A., 1892 (Box 15, Folder 112)
    - Bates, Harry Maynard, 1894 (Box 15, Folder 113)
    - Bayard, Louise, 1891 (Box 15, Folder 114)
    - Biographical sketch of James Burrill Angell, correspondence relating to, 1936-1937 (Box 15, Folder 115)
    - Boardman, Frank Crawford, 1932 (Box 15, Folder 115A)
    - Borton, Rev. John N., 1937 (Box 15, Folder 115B)
    - British Psychological Society
      - Correspondence, 1932 (Box 15, Folder 116)
      - Announcements, 1932-1937 (Box 15, Folder 117)
    - British Universities Quinquennial Meeting, 1931 (Box 15, Folder 118)
    - Brooks, J.B., 1881 (Box 15, Folder 119)
    - Buck, Albert F., 1893-1898 (Box 15, Folder 120)
    - Bulkley, Harry C., 1892-1894 (Box 15, Folder 121)
    - The Canadian Club, 1937 (Box 15, Folder 121A)
    - Carnegie Corporation, 1920-1921 (Box 15, Folder 122)
    - Carrow, Flemming, 1894 (Box 15, Folder 123)
    - Case, Mary S., 1937 (Box 15, Folder 123A)
    - Cattell, J. McK., 1894-1899 (Box 15, Folder 124)
    - Century Association (with newsletter for 1931), 1921-1937 (Box 15, Folder 125)
    - Chapin, Edward, 1882 (Box 15, Folder 126)
    - China, 1895 (Box 15, Folder 127)
      - includes: Sir Robert Hart
    - Clark, Charles E., 1946 (Box 15, Folder 128)
    - Clark, Frederick C., 1893 (Box 15, Folder 129)
    - Clarkson Portrait, 1922-1923 (Box 15, Folder 130)
    - Codd, Mr. and Mrs. George, 1891-1894 (Box 15, Folder 131)
    - Coeducation, reaction to Mr. Angell's article on, 1902-1903 (Box 15, Folder 132)
    - Coffin, Maryanne B., 1893 (Box 15, Folder 133)
    - Coggeshell, H.A., 1891 (Box 15, Folder 134)
    - Collier, Dr. Peter, 1891 (Box 15, Folder 135)
    - Condon, Annie, 1892-1894 (Box 15, Folder 136)
    - Cooley, T.B., 1891-1894 (Box 15, Folder 137)
    - Council on Foreign Relations, Inc.
      - Correspondence, 1924-1932 (Box 16, Folder 138)
      - Fifteen year record, by-laws, reports, descriptive booklet of library, 1921-1936 (Box 16, Folder 139)
      - Program of Conference for University Men and invitations to dinners, 1927-1936 (Box 16, Folder 140)
      - Newsletter, 1933-1937 (Box 16, Folder 141)
      - Confidential Memoranda, 1928-1935 (Box 16, Folder 142)
    - Crampton, Henry E., 1936 (Box 16, Folder 142A)
    - Crane, Sara Walter, 1893-1894 (Box 16, Folder 143)
    - Damon, Alice Harper, 1892 (Box 16, Folder 144)
    - Delabarre, E.B., 1894 (Box 16, Folder 145)
    - Detroit Trust Company, 1934 (Box 16, Folder 146)
    - Dewey, John, 1891-1894 (Box 16, Folder 147)